"The Best Diet for COVID and Long-COVID"
What’s the role of nutrition for both
preventing and beating COVID-19?
Nutrition-related myths
on protection and treatment
have been widely
prevalent in this pandemic,
and while there is no diet
that completely prevents infection
there are certainly dietary steps
we can take to minimize risk.
Those with healthier diets
in general, seem to suffer
less serious courses, but this appears
to be an indirect benefit
of lower rates of obesity
and pre-existing medical conditions.
I mean, that’s great, but is there any diet
that may have direct effects
on the course of disease
or susceptibility
to infection in the first place?
Well, plant-based diets
have been shown to decrease
the risk of suffering from other
respiratory infections—in fact,
plant-based seminaries
during the pandemic of 1918
appeared to have been
relatively spared.
Why might a plant-based diet help?
Vegetable nitrates concentrated
in dark green leafy vegetables
can be used to make nitric oxide,
which is part of our lungs’ first line
of defense against infection.
There are also polyphenol
phytonutrients in plants
that may directly inhibit
viral infection.
Then there are beneficial
effects on our microbiome,
which plays a key role in our
system-wide immune function.
Fiber-containing foods facilitate
more of a symbiotic relationship
with our gut bugs, whereas
processed junk and animal foods
can have the opposite,
dysbiotic effect.
Fiber, concentrated
in whole plant foods,
is the single most anti-inflammatory
food component,
whereas saturated fat, concentrated
in meat, dairy, and junk,
is the most pro-inflammatory
food component.
And so, no surprise
those consuming
more pro-inflammatory diets
were at greater risk
of suffering a severe course,
and of getting COVID-19
in the first place,
up to nearly
twelve times the odds,
even after taking
into account body weight,
diabetes, and blood pressure.
But this study only covered
60 COVID patients.
How about 11,000 COVID patients?
Diet-associated
inﬂammation increased
the risk of getting
COVID-19 infection,
suffering a severe course
and dying from the disease.
Might this help explain
why the COVID death rates
were a hundred times
lower in Africa?
Can a plant-based diet
help mitigate
COVID-19? Let’s find out.
In this study of COVID-19 illness
severity in the elderly
in relation to vegetarian versus
non-vegetarian diets, statistically,
the nonvegetarians had up to
like 20 times the odds
of suffering a critically
severe course of COVID,
but that was based
on only nine vegetarians.
Now here, a study of thousands
of front-line healthcare workers
across six countries found that
those eating plant-based diets
had 73 percent lower odds
of suffering a moderate
or severe course
of COVID-19,
and even combined
with pescatarians
(who eat fish but no other meat)
still had significantly lower odds.
The biggest spread was between
those eating plant-based
versus low-carb.
Compared to plant-based
healthcare workers,
those eating low carb,
high-protein diets had nearly
four times greater odds of suffering
a serious infection.
This may not seem
surprising given that many
of the underlying risk factors
for COVID-19 mortality—obesity,
heart disease, high blood pressure,
and type 2 diabetes—
can be controlled or even
reversed with a healthy enough
plant-based diet and lifestyle.
But the apparent plant-based
protection went above and beyond.
The greatly reduced risk was
independent of all those conditions.
The researchers suggest
that a "healthy diet
rich in nutrient-dense foods
may be considered for protection
against severe COVID-19."
The one food group most associated
with lower symptom severity
in one outpatient study was legumes,
followed by grains, the top sources
of dietary fiber.
The investigators suggest
that the anti-inflammatory effects
of the short-chain fatty acids
released by our fiber-feeding
good gut bugs may explain
the connection.
The healthcare worker study
enrolled a few thousand people,
but Harvard researchers
collected data
from nearly 600,000 participants
using a plant-based diet
scoring system where you get
points for eating healthy plant foods,
but points deducted for meat,
eggs, junk, and dairy.
And indeed those scoring
higher not only had
a significantly lower risk of suffering
a severe course of COVID-19,
but also a significantly lower risk
of getting infected
in the first place.
And again, this was after taking
comorbidities into account,
alongside nondietary risk factors
such as exercise and smoking.
The bottom line: "the best
available evidence suggests
that plant-based diets are beneﬁcial
in directly reducing the risk
of severe COVID-19 symptoms
and the risk of infection,"
even independent of other
health-related factors.
A more Mediterranean-style
diet may reduce the risk
of infection by 22 percent,
while an even more
plant-based diet
may cut infection risk in half.
For dealing with long COVID, a plant-
based diet has been suggested
based on the abundance of data
showing positive associations
of plant-based diets
with improved immune function,
neurotransmitter balance, pain
and inﬂammation reduction,
improved sleep, and mental health.
So, in terms of lifestyle adjustments
in long-COVID management,
"large-scale promotion
of plant-based eating"
may have the potential to improve
physical and mental impacts,
but this has yet
to be put to the test.
There was a study that suggested
that those who eat more vegetables
are less likely to end up depressed,
and those who eat more nuts,
beans, and whole grains
may end up less depressed, anxious,
and stressed after COVID-19,
whereas stress levels were
correlated with higher meat intake.
But the only interventional
studies are like this,
showing a detrimental impact
on high-fat high-sugar diets,
but that’s in Syrian hamsters,
though there are definitely
some unhappy hamster lungs
on the crappy diet.
All in all, adopting
a healthy plant-based diet
may be a powerful tool to decrease
the risk of severe COVID-19
and should be promoted as
a public health safety measure.
And what are the side-effects?
A delay in aging
and decreased disease.
Maybe this is the booster we need.
After all, if real effort
had gone into encouraging
and incentivizing healthier diets
and lifestyles,
we would not only have saved
many more lives from COVID-19,
but we would also reduce
future mortality
from all major causes of death.